<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>1 on World Wide Webber</title>
    <link>/publication-type/1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 1 on World Wide Webber</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy;{year} Jim Webber</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 10:24:24 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/publication-type/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Performance Study of Epoch-based Commit Protocols in Distributed OLTP Databases</title>
      <link>/publication/2022-srds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2022-srds/</guid>
      <description>Distributed OLTP systems execute the high- overhead, two-phase commit (2PC) protocol at the end of every distributed transaction. Epoch-based commit proposes that 2PC be executed only once for all transactions processed within a time interval called an epoch. Increasing epoch duration allows more transactions to be processed before the common 2PC. It thus reduces 2PC overhead per transaction, increases throughput but also increases average transaction latency. Therefore, required is the ability to choose the right epoch size that offers the desired trade-off between throughput and latency. To this end, we develop two analytical models to estimate throughput and average latency in terms of epoch size taking into account load and failure conditions. Simulations affirm their accuracy and effectiveness. We then present epoch-based multi-commit which, unlike epoch- based commit, seeks to avoid all transactions being aborted when failures occur, and also performs identically when failures do not occur. Our performance study identifies workload factors that make it more effective in preventing transaction aborts and concludes that the analytical models can be equally useful in predicting its performance as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pick &amp; Mix Isolation Levels: Mixed Serialization Graph Testing</title>
      <link>/publication/2022-tpctc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2022-tpctc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preserving reciprocal consistency in distributed graph databases</title>
      <link>/publication/2020-papoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2020-papoc/</guid>
      <description>Reciprocal consistency is at the heart of dependable distributed graph databases. This work examines methods for preserving reciprocal consistency and thus data correctness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Design and Evalution of an Edge-based Concurrency Protocol for Distributed Graph Databases</title>
      <link>/publication/2019-epew/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2019-epew/</guid>
      <description>A novel concurrency control mechanism for distributed graph databases that aborts any transaction that could introduce inconsistencies, along with peformance evaluation</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ACTiCLOUD: Enabling the Next Generation of Cloud Applications</title>
      <link>/publication/2017-icdcs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jun 2017 09:00:00 +0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2017-icdcs/</guid>
      <description>An overview of the ACTiCLOUD project for adaptable, data-intensive cloud workloads.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigations on path indexing for graph databases</title>
      <link>/publication/2016-pelga/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2016-pelga/</guid>
      <description>Results of an investigation into path indexing for graph databases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A programmatic introduction to Neo4j</title>
      <link>/publication/2012-splash/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2012 09:00:00 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2012-splash/</guid>
      <description>A tutorial for learning to program with Neo4j&amp;rsquo;s graph model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Horizontally Scalable Graph Database</title>
      <link>/publication/2012-euro-data-forum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2012 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2012-euro-data-forum/</guid>
      <description>Prelimary work on support for supporting very large data sets in graph databases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Role of Hypermedia in Distributed System Development</title>
      <link>/publication/2010-ws-rest/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2010 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2010-ws-rest/</guid>
      <description>Demonstrating practical RESTful business protocols with framework support from Restfulie.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Soya: a Programming Model and Runtime Environment for Component Composition using SSDL</title>
      <link>/publication/2007-acm-cbse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2007 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2007-acm-cbse/</guid>
      <description>An implementation of SSDL tooling and an empirical demonstration of how developers can readily use SSDL to build robust services and systems of services.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Expressing and Reasoning about Service Contracts in Service-Oriented Computing</title>
      <link>/publication/2006-ieee-scc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2006 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2006-ieee-scc/</guid>
      <description>Using SSDL to reason about message exchange patterns (or business protocols) between autonomous services.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Secure and Provable Service Support for Human-Intensive Real-Estate Processes</title>
      <link>/publication/2006-ieee-icws/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2006 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2006-ieee-icws/</guid>
      <description>A realistic workflow appliation for real-estate using SSDL to reason about correctness of multiparty protocols over the Internet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First International Workshop on Design of Service-Oriented Applications (WDSOA&#39;05)</title>
      <link>/publication/2005-wdsoa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2005 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2005-wdsoa/</guid>
      <description>Organising and editing the proceedings of a workshop on the design of service-oriented systems alongside ICSOC 2005.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing the Risk and Value of Adopting Emerging and Unstable Web Services Specifications</title>
      <link>/publication/2004-ieee-scc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2004 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2004-ieee-scc/</guid>
      <description>A framework for reasoning about an immature and chaotic set of protocols and standards for building potentially long-lived systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grid Computing using Web Services Technologies</title>
      <link>/publication/2004-delos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jun 2004 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2004-delos/</guid>
      <description>Showing how large-scale Grid computing designed as a service-oriented architecture and implemented by standard Web Services.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The WS-GAF Registry Service</title>
      <link>/publication/2004-ggf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2004 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2004-ggf/</guid>
      <description>The WS-GAF Registry Service is a naming and metadata service which allows clients to late bind (in a limited fashion) to services as part of a larger grid application.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Misplaced Comma: Programmers’ Tales and Traditions</title>
      <link>/publication/2002-ppig/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2002 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2002-ppig/</guid>
      <description>Thinking about how programmers interact, the stories they tell, and how they impact software engineering.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visual, Object-Oriented Development of Parallel Applications</title>
      <link>/publication/2000-ieee-visual-languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2000 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2000-ieee-visual-languages/</guid>
      <description>The Vorlon hybrid textual-visual parallel programming language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gotos Considered Harmful and Other Programmers&#39; Taboos</title>
      <link>/publication/2000-ppig/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2000 10:24:24 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/2000-ppig/</guid>
      <description>Thinking about programmers&amp;rsquo; susperstitions and taboos and the effects they have on software development.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
